Guide to the Nicolas Nabokov Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nicolas Nabokov papers
1928-1977
GEN MSS 1154
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.35
(6 boxes)
Nabokov, Nicolas, 1903-1978
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series I. Correspondence, 1928-1980. II. Music and Writings, 1927-1999.
Nicolas Nabokov (1903-1978)
American composer of Russian birth; cousin of Russian-American author Vladimir Nabokov, and husband of photographer Dominique Nabokov.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Dominique Nabokov on the Edith and Richard French Fund and the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, music, and writings, most 1928-1930s or 1960s-1970s, with some later correspondence and notes of Dominque Nabokov. Most correspondence is with musicians, including Pierre Boulez, Paul Collaer, Roger Désormière, Wilhelm Furtwängler, Aram Khachaturian, Lina Prokofiev, Igor Markevitch, Igor Stravinsky, and Virgil Thomson. Other correspondents include Vladimir Nabokov and members of the Nabokov family, 1932-1977. Music and writings include Ode: Méditation sur la majesté de Dieu, a ballet-oratorio, autograph manuscript full score and vocal score, 1927 and undated, and printed vocal scores (Editions Maurice Senart, c1928); libretti, correspondence, and printed materials relating to other ballets, oratorios, and operas, 1920s-1990s; a typescript draft of Bagázh: memoirs of a Russian cosmopolitan (New York: Atheneum, 1975), undated; and drafts of writings about Igor Stravinsky, 1960s-1970s.
Ballets; Ballets -- Scores; Composers -- United States; Oratorios; Oratorios -- Scores; Operas -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Boulez, Pierre, 1925-2016; Collaer, Paul, 1891-1989; Désormière, Roger, 1898-1963; Furtwängler, Wilhelm, 1886-1954; Khachaturi͡an, Aram, 1903-1978; Markevitch, Igor, 1912-1983; Nabokov, Dominique; Nabokov, Nicolas, 1903-1978; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977; Prokofiev, Lina, 1897-1989; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989
- Correspondence, 1928-1980; Series I; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent or subject, followed by unsorted
  - Allilueva, Svetlana, 1968 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bayer, Herbert, and Bayer, Joella, 1974-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berlin, Isaiah, and Berlin, Aline, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Berliner Festspiele, 1969, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bethmann Hollweg, Felix von, 1928-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blacher, Boris, 1968, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Boulanger, Nadia, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boulez, Pierre, 1968-1970s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brandt, Willy, and Bahr, Egon, 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Collaer, Paul, 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cuvelier, Marcel, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Daniélou, Alain, 1966-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Désormière, Roger, and Désormière, Colette, 1928-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Diaghilev festival (Monte-Carlo, 1969), 1968-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Franck, Louis, and Menuhin, Yehudi, 1930-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Furtwängler, Wilhelm, 1934-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hofmannsthal, Raimund von, and Hofmannsthal, Elizabeth von, 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Iwaszkiewicz, Jarosław, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kallin, Anna, 1967-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kessler, Harry, Graf, 1929-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Khachaturi︠a︡n, Aram, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Klopfenstein, René, 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Kochno, Boris, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Kollek, Teddy, 1968-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Liebermann, Rolf, 1968-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lopatnikoff, Nikolai, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Markevitch, Igor, and Markevitch, Topazia, 1933-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Morris, Brewster H., and Morris, Helen, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Nabokov, Vladimir; Nabokova, Vera; and Nabokov, Dmitri, 1932-1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New York City Ballet, and Cage, Betty, 1965-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Ormandy, Eugene, 1944-1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Poulenc, Francis, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Prokofiev, Lina, and Prokofiev, Oleg, 1968-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Propes, A. Z. (Fesṭival ha-Yiśreʼeli), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Rothschild, Alix, baroness de, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Rothschild, Philippe, baron de, and Rothschild, Pauline, baroness de, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1968-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Schmid, Carlo, 1970, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Schütz, Klaus, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Souvarine, Boris, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Spender, Stephen, 1959-1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Stein, Werner, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Stravinsky, Igor, and Stravinsky, Vera, 1944-1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Stravinsky festival (Paris and Berlin, 1980), 1977-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Stravinsky festival (Paris and Berlin, 1980) (notes and printed material), 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Stuckenschmidt, Hans Heinz, 1968-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Tehran festival (Tehran, Iran, 1968), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Thomson, Virgil, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Unsorted letters from musicians, 1920s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Unsorted letters about music festivals, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Other unsorted letters in English, 1920s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Other unsorted letters in French, 1920s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 52-54)
  - Other unsorted letters in German, 1920s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Other unsorted letters in Russian, 1920s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 56-59)
- Music and Writings, 1927-1999; Series II; 1.3; (4 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title
  - Bagázh: Memoirs of a Russian Cosmopolitan (memoir)
    - Typescript, with revisions, undated (Box 3, Folder 60-63)
    - Printed material, 1976, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Don Quixote (ballet; libretto by Nabokov and George Balanchine)
    - Synopsis and libretto (manuscript and typescript), and photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Printed material, 1965-1997, undated (Box 4, Folder 66-67)
  - "The Gracious Master" (biography of Igor Stravinsky). Typescript, with revisions, [1970s] (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Job (oratorio; libretto by Jacques Maritain). Libretto fragments, correspondence, and printed material, 1929-1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - The Last Flower (ballet; after James Thurber). Manuscript music fragment and correspondence, 1944, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Love's Labour's Lost (opera; libretto by W. H. Auden and Chester Kallman, after William Shakespeare)
    - Libretto, German and English (typescript photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Related writings by Nabokov and Kallmann, reviews, and other printed material, 1973-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 73-74)
  - The Nutcracker (film scenario by Nabokov and George Balanchine, after E. T. A. Hoffmann)
    - Scenario (typescript and manuscript), undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1999, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Ode: Méditation sur la majesté de Dieu (ballet-oratorio; libretto by Roger Désormière, after Mikhail Vasilʹevich Lomonosov)
    - Full score (autograph manuscript), undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 87-89)
    - Vocal score (autograph manuscript), 1927 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 90)
    - Vocal score (printed, Editions Maurice Senart). Photocopy, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 91)
    - Vocal score (printed, Editions Maurice Senart), c1928 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 92)
  - Paul et Virginie (opera; libretto by Jean Cocteau and Raymond Radiguet). Libretto, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Der Tod des Grigorij Rasputin (opera; libretto by Nabokov and Stephen Spender)
    - Scenario in English (typescript), undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Libretto in English, by Spender (autograph manuscript and typescript), undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Libretto and set design, in English, Act I (typescript carbon), undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Libretto in French (typescript mimeograph), undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Printed material, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - "A Partisan Chronicle" (about Igor Stravinsky). Typescript and autograph manuscript, [1960s] (Box 5, Folder 84)
    Scope and Contents
    Published by Colloquium Verlag, Berlin, 1964.
  - "The Peasant Marriage" (notes for lecture about Les noces, by Igor Stravinsky,). Typescript photocopy, with revisions, undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Variations on a Theme by Tchaikovsky (cello and orchestra). Printed program from performance, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 86)